Guide to the Gennett Lumber Company Records, 1832-1954, bulk 1920-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Gennett Lumber Company records 1832-1954, bulk 1920-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Gennett Lumber Company (Asheville, N.C.).
19 Linear Feet Approximately 16,000 Items
Lumber company founded in 1902 by Andrew and Nat Gennett, headquartered in Georgia and South Carolina, later in Asheville, N.C.
Correspondence, contracts, legal documents, and other records of the Gennett Lumber Co., mostly for the years 1920 to 1945. The two Gennett brothers Nat and Andrew, founders of the company, were part of the effort to establish the South's national forest system. Subjects covered by materials in the collection include Civil War reminiscences, life at Nashville and at Tulane and Vanderbilt universities shortly after the war, the lumber business after 1890, economic conditions in the U.S. after 1900, forest conservation, U.S. politics and foreign relations during World War I, and travel in Europe after the war.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gennett Lumber Company Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in April 1957.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, contracts, legal documents, and other records of the Gennett Lumber Co., mostly for the years 1920 to 1945. The two Gennett brothers Nat and Andrew, founders of the company, were part of the effort to establish the South's national forest system. Subjects covered by materials in the collection include Civil War reminiscences, life at Nashville and at Tulane and Vanderbilt universities shortly after the war, the lumber business after 1890, economic conditions in the U.S. after 1900, forest conservation, U.S. politics and foreign relations during World War I, and travel in Europe after the war.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Gennett family
Gennett Lumber Company (Asheville, N.C.).
Tulane University -- Students
Vanderbilt University -- Students
Forests and forestry -- United States
Lumber trade -- Georgia
Lumber trade -- North Carolina
Lumber trade -- South Carolina
Universities and colleges -- Southern States
World War, 1914-1918
Industries -- North Carolina -- Asheville
Industries -- Georgia
Nashville (Tenn.)--Social life and customs
Southern States -- Economic conditions
United States -- Foreign relations -- 1913-1921
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives, Confederate
United States -- Politics and government -- 1913-1921
Related Material
Autobiography of Andrew Gennett IV (Rubenstein Library Microfilm #101-1-1). The autobiography chiefly concerns Gennett's personal experiences and family history.
Contents of Collection
- Business Records Series, 1832-1954, (29 boxes)
  - Contract Files (Box 1)
  - Union County, Georgia contracts (Box 1)
  - Chattahoochee National Forest (Box 1)
  - United States Department of Agriculture (Box 1)
  - North Carolina contracts (Box 1)
  - Contract Files (Box 2)
  - Timber Sales (Box 3)
  - Government Land Exchange (Box 3)
  - Business Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Contract Files (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with the Department of Justice, Northern District of Georgia (Box 4)
  - Contract Files: Georgia, Kentucky, and North Carolina (Box 5)
  - Contract Files (Box 6-8)
  - Contract Files: Kentucky (Box 9)
  - Contract Files: North Carolina, South Carolina, and Tennessee (Box 10)
  - Contract Files: North Carolina (Box 11)
  - IRS Documents (Box 12)
  - Yearly Earnings (Box 12)
  - Federal Taxes Withheld (Box 12)
  - Abstract of the Lands of N.W. and Andrew Gennett (Box 12)
  - Volumes of Accounts (Box 13)
  - Accounts (Box 14)
  - Contract Files: Clarkesville, GA (Box 15)
  - Partnership Agreement, 1942 (Box 15)
  - Business Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Contract Files (Box 16)
  - H. P. Campbell Papers, Mill and Purchase Papers, 1946-1949 (Box 16)
  - Timber Sales, 1941-1948 (Box 16)
  - Insurance (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1952 (Box 17)
  - Clippings (Box 17)
  - Timber Sales, 1938-1944 (Box 18)
  - Contract Files (Box 19)
  - H. P. Campbell Papers (Box 19)
  - Contract Files (Box 20)
  - H. P. Campbell Papers and Purchase Papers, 1950-1952 (Box 20)
  - Contract Files: Georgia and North Carolina (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous Real Estate (Box 21)
  - Social Security File (Box 21)
  - Asheville Country Club (Box 21)
  - Contract Files: Georgia and North Carolina (Box 22)
  - Government Timber Offerings, 1947-1948 (Box 22)
  - Contract Files (Box 23)
  - General Correspondence (Box 23)
  - Contract Files: North Carolina and Pennsylvania (Box 24)
  - Contract Files: North Carolina (Box 25)
  - Business Correspondence (Box 25)
  - Legal Documents (Box 25)
  - Wachovia Bank Papers (Box 25)
  - Contract Files: North Carolina (Box 26)
  - Business Correspondence (Box 26)
  - Investment Registry (Box 26)
  - Contract Files (Box 27)
  - Unpaid Bills (Box 27)
  - Contract Files: North Carlina and Ohio (Box 28)
  - Business Correspondence, 1929-1936 (Box 28)
  - Santeetlah Operation (Box 28)
  - Bound Anthologies (Box 29)
  - Ledger, 1942 Aug.-1944 Oct. (Box 30)
  - Invoices: New Bridge, N.C., 1945 May-1947 Dec. (Box 30)
  - Invoices: Hayesville, N.C., 1945 Jan.-1947 Dec. (Box 30)
  - Invoices: Hayesville, N.C., 1943 Sept.-1944 Dec. (Box 31)
  - Invoices: Beattyville, Ky., 1945 Jan-1949 Sept. (Box 31)
  - Invoices: Beattyville, Ky., 1943 Sept. 15-1944 Dec. 16 (Box 32)